I'm going to start my message tonight with a clip from a movie, not yet, not yet, people in the back, you got a few moments.
I want to start with a clip from a movie, because we've been trying to explore big questions over the last few weeks, over the last few sessions during our encounter gathering.
We talked about one of the big questions might be, some of us as we're going into college or whatever phase of life that we're in, some of us might be asking a big question, well, where do I belong?
So we started this fall series talking about, like, hey, God wants you to belong to him.
God shows you radical grace.
God welcomes you as his family, as a follower of Christ, all those things.
And we can experience that in community together.
Community is a radical grace where we're not only receiving that but committed to showing that radical grace to one another.
And so that was one of the big questions.
Where do I belong?
And I hope that these life groups that we're in, our campus ministry, can help be a place of belonging for us.
Last week we talked about purpose, why am I here.
Trying to explore the question, like, hey, not just major, not just career, not just those kinds of choices,
but really the deep down purpose of why am I here, what purpose do I have, what should I live for,
and starting to explore that as we try and find the purpose.
It's not as much trying to find a purpose on our own, but God gives us purposes.
God gives us things to live for.
God gives us a direction to go in.
The last question that we want to explore as we go into tonight is the question of identity.
Who am I?
Look at the person next to you and ask them, who are you?
And what I want to do to just kind of breach, is that the right term?
Broach the subject?
I don't know what the word is.
approach this subject is to show a clip from a movie that I feel like really highlights
one of the main characters who's having an identity crisis moment.
And actually, throughout the whole movie, this main character, he has this identity crisis,
and you kind of see his progression through how he finds this answer to this identity crisis,
How he explores this, how he tries to find an answer.
And what's really fascinating for me, I'm not going to spoil the movie.
Well, hopefully I'm not going to spoil the movie, although the clip I'm going to show is going to spoil some things.
But I hope I'm not spoiling too much by saying some things like this.
This identity crisis, this crisis that this main character has when he asks or has to confront the question of who am I,
it causes a good amount of tension throughout the movie.
It ends up being one of the main sources of conflict in the movie.
There's conflict between one of the main characters and the other.
There's factions that develop behind these main characters as they're trying to explore their identity and their identities.
And even as he goes on this journey, he's trying to find it, and he finds it in some really interesting places.
I'm not going to go into all of it, but just to give you some background for this clip,
he goes on this journey trying to resolve this identity crisis.
He tries to, like, subscribe to different people's philosophies of what my identity should be and all these things.
And he's, like, latching on, like, oh, no, these are my people now, or I can subscribe to this and have this ideology.
And that defines me as a person.
That defines me as a being, as a character in this movie.
And so he goes through this whole thing, and it culminates in this discussion where we realize that a lot of these questions came because this main character's identity was based on another person.
And when that fell apart, he started to wrestle with these questions and explore this question of identity.
So I'm going to ask us in just a moment to watch this clip and then process it together.
I do need to give a disclaimer, and you'll see why in just a moment.
This movie, I did not watch it by my choice.
Just going to say that. You'll understand why in about five seconds.
And so let's watch this clip together, and then we'll process it. Sound good?
Cool. People come back if we can play it, and then we'll go on.
How many of you have never seen the Barbie movie?
Really?
Actually, a lot of dudes.
That's by far not surprising.
Again, I didn't choose to watch it.
I chose to be married to my lovely wife, who chose to watch it together.
But that being said, hopefully the points that I made before the clip start now making sense a little bit.
Again, if you haven't watched the full movie, you may not fully get the impact of this.
But Ken of Barbie and Ken.
By the way, who's never grown up with Barbie?
Like, never had an idea of who Barbie was?
Like, you all know at least who Barbie?
Toy? Toy Barbie? Yeah? Cool?
Like, I don't need to explain toys? Yeah? Cool? Okay.
Ken is having an identity crisis.
Who is he if not for Barbie?
It's Barbie and Ken. It's Barbie and Ken. It's Barbie and Ken.
And throughout the movie, it affects his relationship with her.
He wants to be Barbie's Ken.
He wants to be in that relationship.
He wants the house.
He wants all of these things.
That's who he is.
That's his identity.
That's his perspective on his life, his hope, his future.
All of these things are wrapped up in this identity.
I am Barbie's Ken.
And then throughout the movie, I mean, you see different things.
He has this whole thing of, like, finding a magazine and all this kind of stuff about the patriarchy.
I'm like, I want to be that.
But then, you know, it kind of falls apart and all this other stuff.
You see the faction develop, the Kens versus the Barbies.
But, you know, it's just movie fun.
I mean, it's not really like, you know, air, it's the whole thing.
I'd like this clip to set up the theme of identity for tonight,
because I think it shows how important having a solid identity is.
Now, when I say this, I don't necessarily need all of us to leave this building,
leave this place, and say, I understand myself.
that's not really what we're after
if you want to do that you can do
what those like those Myers-Briggs
things is that still a thing
do you guys know all your Myers-Briggs things
INFJ I think that's me still
I always ask my wife am I INFJ
and she's like yes I'm like alright
Enneagrams any other nines
in the room
cool anybody not know what Enneagrams
are
anyone think Enneagrams are from the devil
yeah there's some people who do
there's a whole thing with that
and there's some history.
Anyways, all that kind of stuff.
My point is not necessarily that we need to have this deeply detailed,
point-by-point understanding of this is who I am,
trying to understand our personalities and wiring and all that kind of stuff.
When I talk about identity, whether we understand it or not,
this self-understanding, the core of who we are,
do we have a proper core?
Do we have a proper core identity?
steep self-understanding that is secure, that is stable in difficult times, that allows us to
live freely in the lives that God has given us. So when I talk about identity, I'm not necessarily
talking about the superficial things like, I'm an engineer, I'm a Korean, I'm an upper middle
class, lower middle class, blah, blah, blah. I'm not talking about those kind of external things.
Again, the deep-rooted understanding of this is who I am that ultimately affects so much about our
lives, how we live, the joys that we have, the stability that we have in difficult times, even
impacting our relationships. If we don't have that proper understanding, then there's ways that it can
actually hurt the people around us in ways that we never intended. And so what we want to talk
about tonight, and again, we don't have the ability, the space, the time to fully explore
this in depth tonight, but I'm hoping that tonight will start a process for us. For me to say, we as
a campus ministry want to help all of you discover this more richly, more fully in the months and the
years to come, but we want to at least start this understanding of finding our identity, and more
specifically, finding our identity in God. And so the one thing for today is this. God wants to bless
you with a new identity in Christ. God wants to bless you with a new identity in Christ. Would you
turn to the person next to you and tell them the one thing for today? I feel like this is also
appropriate. Would you also turn to the person next to you and tell them you are Canuff? If you
get that. Canuff is the whole thing. Genesis 32. Genesis 32. We're going to look at this
narrative from the Old Testament, this story that is describing what this person Jacob went through
and specifically how God uses this idea of identity to work in Jacob's life.
And so Genesis 32, verses 22 through 28.
If you have Bibles or phones, if you want to track along there.
If you don't, you can follow along on the screen behind.
But Genesis 32, verses 22 through 28.
I'll read that for us tonight.
It says this.
the same night he being jacob uh the same night he arose and took his two wives his two female
servants and his 11 children and crossed the fort of the jebbuk he took them and sent them across
the stream and everything else that he had and jacob was left alone and a man wrestled with him
until the breaking of the day when the man saw that he did not prevail against jacob he touched
his hip socket and Jacob's hip was put out of joint as he wrestled with him and he said let me
go for the day has broken but Jacob said I will not let you go unless you bless me and he said to him
what is your name and he said Jacob then he said your name shall no longer be called Jacob
but Israel. For you have striven with God and with men and have prevailed. Amen. We'll stop there.
Can I pray for us one more time before we dig into the word tonight? God, I pray for your help
talking about identity. I feel like it's simple enough to talk about concepts where we find
identity, how we can find it in you. But God, I know the more difficult thing is to believe in
faith that there is a God of the universe who has created, who has loved us, and who has given us a
better identity than we can ever discover for ourselves or that we can ever find in anything
else. God, that takes work. There's a fight going on for even some of my brothers and sisters' souls
here in this room, that they would choose not to believe, but rather believe other things about
them. So God, I pray for your help. I pray that you'd minister to all of us, speak your grace
into our lives, that as we explore this idea of identity, you would help us find it in you.
And so speak to us, we pray all this in Jesus' name. As we dig into this passage again, the bigger
idea or the theme that we want to explore is this theme of identity. But to do so, we need to
understand Jacob and his story, how he's gotten here. And so there's this crisis moment that this
portion of scripture describes, but even before that we want to see who was Jacob and where was
Jacob before the crisis. If you know Jacob's family of origin, you know some of his narrative,
his story, his background. You know his grandfather, his grandfather Abraham, great figure given a
promise by God. Hey, Abraham, I'm going to make you a father of many nations. I'm going to bless
you with people, property, possessions. You're going to go into this promised land. You're going
You're going to become this great nation that eventually becomes the people of Israel.
I'm going to make you this great nation, and I'm going to bless you.
And actually, through you, all nations on the earth will be blessed.
All families on the earth will be blessed.
And so Abraham is his grandfather.
He's given this great big promise by God.
He has this wonderful thing that he's doing, that God is doing in his family.
Abraham's son Isaac eventually gets married to Rebekah.
Isaac, I mean, he's given the promise too, not as active.
There's other things going on.
But one interesting thing between Isaac and Rebekah, his wife,
is they end up having two sons, Jacob and his brother Esau.
And one thing that really starts defining this family is favoritism.
There's favoritism between Esau and Jacob.
Hey, Isaac, he loves the older son.
He loves Esau.
He loves how he can hunt and bring meat to the house and all that kind of stuff.
But Rebekah loves Jacob more, and there's more favoritism there.
So there's this whole family dynamic of favoritism and the dynamics that happen.
And so that brings him to Jacob and his older brother Esau.
Esau is the older brother. He's the firstborn.
He's given all the promises. He's given all the blessings, all that kind of stuff.
So he has this family of origin.
He has these weird dynamics going on, favoritism, this idea of spiritual blessing that's happening.
And in the midst of all that family of origin, you see Jacob.
And you see, one of the biggest things that characterizes him throughout Scripture, throughout all the different chapters and passages that describe him, there's a constant striving that he goes through as he goes throughout his life.
There's one story where he talks to Esau.
Esau's coming in after a hunt, and he's hungry and all that stuff.
And so he strives by scheming.
He strives by scheming, saying, hey, Esau, I'll feed you.
I'll make some stew.
I'll feed you.
If and only if you give me your birthright.
And so he schemes, saying, Jacob, you are, sorry, Esau, you are the older son.
You're supposed to be given all of this as the firstborn son.
You're supposed to be given all this blessing for your firstborn son.
You are starving.
I'll feed you if.
And then there's the scheme.
I want your birthright, and then I'll give you a bowl of soup.
There's this later instance.
Yes, he's given the birthright by Esau.
That's half of the equation.
But he needs to talk to his father Isaac and get the blessing from Isaac.
It can't just be given to him by his brother Esau, although he did give it to him for a bowl of soup.
He has to get it from Isaac.
And so what does he do?
If you know the story, you know that he tricks his father.
He lies to his father.
He deceives.
He schemes by lying to his father Isaac.
Hey, I know I'm really your firstborn son.
Bless me instead of Esau.
He lies.
He deceives.
He gets this amazing, not just family blessing, but like this powerful covenantal blessing.
All the blessings that God was supposed to give Abraham, it continues on through his family line.
Isaac steals, oh, sorry, Jacob steals it away from his older brother Esau and lies to his father in order to do that.
You see him striving by running away because Esau realizes what he's done.
He's stolen the blessing, so Jacob runs away.
That's part of his striving.
I'm going to run away to save my life because my brother wants to kill me.
He finds his uncle, and I don't have time to go through it.
But he ends up marrying two women, both daughters of his uncle.
There's all sorts of weird things going on.
Two things I just want to say.
One spouse is enough.
Turn to the person next to you and say, one is enough.
Also tell them, don't marry your cousin.
I just have to get that out there.
I don't have time to get into it.
But he goes to his uncle.
He builds this big family.
He builds wealth.
He has his uncle Laban's livestock and all this.
And he schemes ultimately to take much of it away as he's running away with his family.
And he runs away again to preserve his own well-being and even material wealth.
He is a constant striver.
He is constantly going, constantly moving, constantly fighting, constantly wanting what is his, trying to get what is his.
He's trying to earn it for himself.
And what we see in multiple instances is that striving is also marked by a life of deception.
See, the name Jacob isn't just a name.
Any Jacobs in the room?
Yeah, there's a few of you.
What I'm about to share, it doesn't need to define you, okay?
You are not the Bible Jacob.
If there's a Jacob near you, point to them and say, you are not the Bible Jacob.
The name Jacob in the Hebrew talks about grasping the heel,
or it's a play on words that can also mean cheater, deceiver.
He who cheats.
Actually, his older brother Esau calls this out in Genesis 27.
is he not rightly names Jacob for he has cheated me these two times he took away my birthright and
behold now he has taken away my blessing see especially in the old testament scriptures
names weren't just names they're not just names that just sound nice or like they they they flow
off the tongue really well or whatever else or it's just oh no one else has this name and so
I'm going to name my kid this and like like that's not there there's meaning there's uh identity
There's destiny that's tied up in these names in the Old Testament scriptures.
And so for Jacob to have this name of Jacob is not only a name, some label that someone
calls him, but an identity marker for him.
He's cheated Isaac.
He's cheated his uncle.
He's cheated his brother.
He deceives in schemes, always deceiving, always scheming, always running.
So much so that at this point in his life story, we have to confront the question,
Is it just a name or is it his core identity?
Again, this self-understanding, the unchanging, stable, consistent core of who you are,
what makes you you, who am I really?
And by the time we hit this narrative, that's where we find Jacob.
And so I want to ask you, before we dig into this passage specifically,
if we consider Jacob's life so far, Jacob's life as he hits this crisis moment,
I want to ask us to think about even our understanding of our own identities.
One question I want to ask is this, who have others told you that you are?
If I had to phrase it differently from your own perspective, from the first person perspective,
it's how you would answer this question, or you would answer the question like this.
I am who my blank tells me I am.
I am who my family of origin tells me that I am.
Again, Jacob has grown up with this.
I am my mom's favorite, but I am not my dad's favorite.
heck they named me cheater
they named me deceiver
and so maybe
that's not only
something my family speaks into my life
but something that is actually defining of me
I don't know if our families
have told us something like that
you're not the golden child
you are the golden child
you're the gifted one, you're the special one
you're not the gifted one, you're not the special one
the more siblings that you have, the more comparison points
that you have, oh you're the athletic one
you're the smart one, you're the one. You're my retirement plan. I don't know if any of your
parents have told you that. But is our identity wrapped up? And whether it's been said to us
explicitly or not, things that our families have told us or pressured us into, or just the way that
you live and operate, it just comes out of you from your family of origin. Maybe it's who have
your friends told you that you are. I know there's some people that I counseled in the past, and they
have these stories or these moments where they realize like, oh, I overperform in my life now
because I've been told my whole life by my friend group, you are the one who holds our friend group
together. You're the peacemaker. You're the one we all go to when we have issues with one another.
You're the one who can make peace. You're the one who can bring us all together. And so there is this
weight that some people feel from their friend groups, from their friends, and they feel this
way, saying, if I don't do what I'm
supposed to do, if I don't be who I'm supposed
to be, then my friend group's going to fall apart,
they're all going to hate each other, and they might even blame
me for it. And so
there's this identity markers that are wrapped up
in their friends, in what they've
spoken. As well-intentioned as their friends
may have been, maybe for
some of us, it's like Ken.
Our relationships
define us.
I am not just Josh,
I am Josh Erica's husband, and that is
my first and foremost
identity. But maybe for some of us, we realize our identity falls apart when we get that text.
I think we're done. I think we should see other people. And maybe you're like, Ken, you start
breaking apart. You start crying. You start weeping. You're like, no, but I'm supposed to be
Ken and Barbie and all that kind of stuff. And you realize, wait, no, this was such an integral part
of who I am that if you end this, I don't know who I am anymore. Maybe there's movements. Maybe
there's, maybe some of us are huge on social media, and I don't know, I've never seen you come across
my feed, but you have this identity that you've curated, that you've put together, that you're
putting out there on the online platforms for all the world to see, and you are who your audience
tells you that you are. You are who your audience likes you for. You're the one who gets the
affirmations, who gets those subscriptions, and you're the one who says, I'm presenting myself to
the world and they're affirming that I am this? Or who does your striving reveal that you are?
Maybe it's other people who have told you, but maybe it's also your striving, your work, your
effort, your performance. What is your striving revealed about who you think you are? I am not
what my family, not what my friends, not these different relationships people. I am not who they
say I am. I am what I do. I am what I achieve. I am all of this. And so in your striving, what are
you after? What are you aiming for? What do you put all of your time, your energy, your attention,
your focus on? And what does that reveal about who you are or who you think that you are? It's not
just that I am putting all this work in to become a liberal arts major. It's not putting all this
effort into becoming a piano performance major. I'm not putting all this effort into becoming an
engineer. It's more like I am putting in all this effort. I am striving so hard. I am going
through sleepless night after night after night after night. I am doing all of this because at
its core I need to be a success. It's not I need to achieve success. I need to be a success. I need
to make something of myself. I need to be someone because of what I've done or achieved. And there
issues, if we find our source of identity from all of these other things. A pastor who's passed
away by now, Tim Keller, he talks about identity, and he talked about it pretty in depth, and he
talks about how crushing it is to find your identity in any of these other things. If your
identity comes from other people, well, then your identity and your well-being, your self-regard goes
up and down with how well you perform at that identity. If your identity, if your main core
identity is wrapped up in, oh, for instance, oh, I am the firstborn child. I'm the firstborn son of
my parents. If that is the essence, the core of your identity, then you might feel a certain level
of self-regard. You might feel a certain high or low, depending on this is how well I'm living up
to the standards that my parents have for me as the firstborn son. My parents will—I am the
firstborn son. My parents—now, I need to say this, especially this week, because a few things. I'm
going to talk about my parents. They are here in Michigan for a long time. They're here for a few
months, and so if you see them at church, do not go up to them and say, Josh talked about you on
Friday, okay? Don't do that, right? I love them. They are wonderful. They have been wonderful.
I have no complaints about them, but I'm trying to express, like, hey, these things might
happen. These things could have happened. My parents have friends, and they have children,
and so they do what parents often do. They compare. Oh, how many teeth does Stephanie have? Eight? Well,
mine only has four. You know, you have all these comparisons, no matter what age you have, even if
it's inconsequential, like teeth. But they compare, and then, you know, one of my mom's friends will
tell her, like, oh yeah, my son bought me a first-class ticket to so-and-so to this resort,
and he paid this wonderful thing and all this stuff.
I'm so thankful that my firstborn son is so generous with his finances
and helps me live just such a wonderful retirement life.
And she tells me that, and she doesn't mean to,
but I feel this tinge inside, this hurt, this pain.
I'm a pastor.
I don't have the income to send my parents on an economy ticket,
much less the first class to get in.
And there's this hurt inside of saying,
man, I know they're not pressuring me to please don't go to them
and say you pressured them into doing this.
Like, no, my parents never did that with me in any regard.
But there's this hurt in me of saying,
man, I wish I could be a better firstborn son for them.
I wish I had better income, a better career, more stability,
ability to provide insurance or all these other things,
cover for my parents.
I wish I could do that.
Again, they don't intend to, but my self-regard starts going down and being like, man, my parents really deserve someone better as their kid.
If your identity comes from other people, there's this performative aspect that directly impacts your well-being.
If I'm not living up or down to certain standards, that directly affects how I'm doing, how I'm living on a day-to-day life.
Even if your identity comes from you.
No one's telling you to do this.
no one's telling you to be this,
still your well-being goes up and down
based on your own metrics of success and failure.
It's up to you to find the right career.
It's up to you to achieve.
It's up to you to perform.
And at the end of the day, it could still be crushing.
Say, man, I failed.
I screwed up.
I didn't get to where I want to be.
I didn't achieve the things I want to be.
Your ambitions might fall short.
Have others told you who you are?
If so, who?
or what does your striving reveal
about who you think you are?
For Jacob, he's had both.
He's had both others speaking to him.
He's had striving and all of this reveals
he is a striver, he is a deceiver,
he is a cheat, he is all of this.
And this has not just become a name for him
and it has become an identity.
So what happens?
Then we have this crisis moment,
the passage that we're reflecting on tonight.
The crisis moment happens in verses,
especially in 22 through 24,
just to set the stage for us.
Jacob escapes his uncle
and he has to go back to where he came from.
And so Jacob was about to face Esau,
his older brother, the firstborn.
Jacob has to face Esau,
the guy he schemed against,
the guy he deceived,
the guy he deceived his dad
to steal his blessing about.
And so Jacob, if you're putting yourself
in Jacob's shoes,
you have to imagine there's some level of fear
that's going through Jacob's heart right now.
It's been years.
I've built a family.
I have all this stuff.
But still, the last thing that I heard
about from my older brother was him wanting to get after me, him wanting to get back at me,
him wanting to kill me for what I stole from him. And so before this, you see, even till this point,
Jacob is scheming. He's going to say, okay, I'm going to set all of these flocks ahead of me and
say, Esau, this is just a gift from me to you. Please don't harbor any bad feelings. I just
want to give this to you. And so he's trying to give it back to him. He's trying to put his family
ahead of him go ahead of him maybe as he sees my wives again one is enough as he sees my wives as
he sees my children he might oh my gosh look at his how cute and how could I ever be mad at the
guy who who gave me like extended family I don't know I don't know what he's thinking but he's still
scheming I'm gonna send all of this ahead of me so that maybe Esau will be in a good mood by the time
I see him again he's about to face him he has fears and so he's scheming I want to save my life
And in this crisis moment, the night before he sees Esau, God meets Jacob at night, and God meets Jacob alone.
Part of it is by Jacob's design.
I'm sending everyone.
I'm pushing everyone forward.
I'm doing all of this kind of stuff.
Part of it was God orchestrating things like, no, I need to meet with him.
And who knows why he's up at night alone.
I don't know if you've had the nights alone when you're just wrestling with everything.
I don't know if you've had those nights where, like, just that one memory from your past is just, like, haunting you awake.
Like, it's just this embarrassing thing.
Like, you're just, like, I don't know why I'm thinking about this.
It was, like, 25 years ago.
But, you know, I asked this girl out this one way, and it was super awkward.
And she just gave me this, like, weird, disgusted look.
And I'm just staring alone on my bed at night and be like, I'm married with a kid.
Why is this coming up right now?
Why can't I go back to sleep?
God, I am so happy with my life.
Please let me go.
But it's, like, the embarrassment, you know, like, that's not what Jacob's going.
But I wonder if at this moment, Jacob's going through a lot and he's also awake.
It's not necessarily embarrassment, it's fear.
It's not embarrassment, it's anxiety.
He's confronting, the knight is confronting him about his thoughts.
Man, by facing Esau, I have to confront my past.
I have to confront my life story up to this point.
Maybe there's something in his thoughts that is keeping him up awake and saying,
man, my life story has only shown this, that I am worthless, that I am a deceiver, that I am a cheat.
I deserve the wrath that is coming from my older brother.
Maybe he's remembering his failures.
Maybe he's remembering, actually, but it's so complicated because he was always dad's favorite growing up.
And, man, he deserved something of it, but still, I did this.
I shouldn't have done that.
There might have been all of this wrestling going on even within Jacob's own head before God says, no, I'm going to meet with him at night and alone.
See, because when God wants to do deep work with a person, sometimes it's in larger group settings, but honestly, a lot of times it's when people get alone with God.
He cared about Jacob and his future enough to say, no, I need to confront him, and I need to confront him alone.
if you think about people in the scripture
even Abraham, his grandfather
when God gave Abraham this promise
it wasn't with all these other people
it was just with him
Abraham, I'm going to isolate you
I'm going to just talk to you
I'm going to give you this promise
I need to deal with you
so that you feel the full weight of the promises
that I'm going to give you
when God calls Moses later
and says, Moses, I need you to bring my people out of slavery
he does that within a burning bush
no one else is around
maybe some sheep, but sheep don't count
He confronts him alone and says, I need to deal with you.
I need to call you.
I need to challenge you because my people need saving from slavery.
There's a prophet later, Elijah.
Elijah's running away, scared for his life.
God confronts Elijah, not in the midst of all of this, not even in the midst of, like, fire and tornadoes and wind and all that stuff.
God meets Elijah alone on the mountainside in the quietness of nothing.
Even, I mean, yes, God and Jesus, Jesus is God and all that stuff.
But even Jesus, as he was on earth, he often sought times to be alone.
He went into the wilderness to be tempted alone.
He had this work that needed to be done alone.
When God wants to do deep work in a person, he gets them alone.
Side point, why do we bother doing things like retreats?
Why do we bother doing things like, hey, let's pray together, let's seek God together?
Something I challenged our leaders with a few weeks ago is the idea of Sabbathing, of stopping and just being with God for a while.
I challenged them with that.
Why is this important?
because God does that deep work when we're alone with him.
Jacob is in his crisis moment.
Jacob is about to face his fears.
Jacob is about to confront, man,
this is the guy who represents the worst about me and my identity,
and God gets him alone to say, I need to work on you.
Can I pause and ask some more questions?
When you think about identity,
when you think about how you understand yourself,
can I ask you some questions?
One, who are you when you stop?
I think for me, I spent so much of my life going, going, going, going, going, going,
not necessarily actually for school.
Once I hit college, man, college hit, I'm like, I am okay with a B.
Bs get degrees, you know, Cs get degrees, Ds get degrees, Ds get degrees.
I'm okay with my B.
I got a solid 3.0 average in undergrad.
Enough to get my piece of paper, right?
That is enough.
I didn't go, go, go, go, go for school.
I went.
I went, went, went.
I strove because I thought I needed to do more for God in the church.
And so my going, going, going, going, going was I need to lead more life groups.
I need to go on more missions projects.
I need to serve more times a week as I'm leading worship, three, four times a week just by myself.
I needed to do all of this.
I needed to meet with these people to counsel these people.
I needed to have all of this on my plate because this is what I'm meant to do because this is who I'm meant to be.
And so I went, went, strove, strove, strove, strove.
And I never stopped to think, man, is this who God wants me to be?
Not what God wants me to do, but is this who God wants me to be?
And so I went and went and went until I became a pastor.
And then I went and I went and I went and I went to seminary or started seminary.
And I went and I went and I went.
And then 2015, it all came crashing down when my church, HMCC of Chicago, we shut down.
For the first time in like 15, 20 years, I stopped doing things for God.
And I was just confronted with, man, when I have nothing left to do, who am I?
Maybe for some of us, we've gone, gone, strove, strove, tried, tried, worked, worked.
And we've done that for so long that we've never stopped and actually asked ourselves the question, who am I?
Or maybe we don't stop because we're afraid of that answer.
If I don't do, is the answer, I'm not good enough, I'm not enough, I'm not worth enough, I'm not valuable enough?
Or, who are you when you're alone?
See, because those are the questions that kind of came up for me.
It wasn't, what should I do?
It wasn't the tasks that I should do, the careers that I should have,
although I had to answer some questions about how I was going to make money after that church closed.
My crisis moment started being these deep existential things.
Was I a good pastor?
Am I a good pastor?
Do I preach well enough?
Am I inspiring enough?
Do I care for people enough?
Do I shepherd people enough?
Am I loving enough?
Am I kind enough?
Am I gracious enough?
Am I gentle enough?
Am I challenging in the right ways enough?
Am I a good pastor?
But actually at a certain point during those years when I wasn't a pastor for a while,
at some point those questions got deeper and harder to face.
I stopped asking the question, was I a good pastor?
Am I a good pastor?
I started asking myself, am I even a good person?
Because I looked at the failure of that church.
I looked at the closure of that church.
And I looked and I examined and I tried to do this autopsy on it.
And I'm thinking, God, this church failed because I am a messed up human being.
I took advantage of people.
I abused my situation and my power.
I manipulated.
I was lazy.
I stopped caring.
I did all of these things.
I hurt people, all these things.
I'm not even a good person.
And I realized I didn't want to stop because I didn't want to think how messed up I really am.
Whatever, even if you don't understand it.
This stable core identity, is it true of you even when you stop working?
Stop doing?
Stop striving?
Have you ever stopped?
When's the last time you were alone with God?
Maybe some of us are afraid because it's not those kinds of things that we're afraid of.
It's not those answers that we're afraid of.
It's more like, I don't want to stop because I'm afraid when I ask who am I,
the question is not I'm a bad person or I've done these bad things.
The answer to the question who am I is I am a broken, damaged person
who has been hurt by people around me.
i am the wounds that people have placed on my life i am the curses that people have spoken
against me i am my worst day or maybe i am the worst thing that i've done for some of us maybe
we don't stop or maybe we stopped and we don't want to stop ever again because we don't want
to think about man i really am these worst things about me things that have been done to me or things
that I've done myself, which leads to a correlated question.
What are you afraid of people knowing about you?
The more that you're afraid to reveal and show parts of your identity,
maybe that's an indicator, actually, that's a deeper part of your identity
than you let on.
As much as you try to come to college to reinvent yourself,
as much as you come to college to say,
I don't have to be that person at the core of who you are.
It's nagging you. It's pulling at you.
It's saying, nope, this is still you. It's still in there. I'm still in there.
The damaged, broken, wounded, or messed up, sinful, terrible person that's inside.
This is Jacob's crisis moment.
Again, as he's facing Esau, as he's facing his fears, as he's facing his anxieties,
this is where God chooses to meet him.
Alone, at night, and really for this purpose,
so that Jacob can receive a better blessing, a transformed identity.
we see in verses 25 to 28
Jacob wrestling
with God
I'm not going to get into it
there's a lot of ideas
or hypotheses about who this guy was
was it God
was it God himself
there's some allusion to that
we didn't read it but verse 30
Jacob says I've seen God face to face
and so maybe it is God directly
God incarnate as a man
there's a person who's very specifically
God become a man
is this a pre-Jesus Jesus
I don't know, could be
could be an angel
Hosea 12 refers to him
as an angel, we're not exactly sure
but a few things, one in the Old Testament
it's just more common for supernatural beings to come in the form
of a man, so we're not sure who exactly
is it, is it God directly, is it
the angel, is it
Jesus, I don't know, but whatever it is
it's some supernatural being representative
of God, why the wrestling
why doesn't God just start
a fire and sit down with Jacob and say
hey bro, let's talk
yo, let's talk. How are you doing?
You worry? You afraid? You anxious?
What's going on, man?
He can make some fish,
you know, grow some s'mores.
That's how people open up, right?
Food. That's why all of your meetups
are all over food, right? Amen?
How many of you guys meet up with your life group leaders and say,
let's wrestle!
And that's where your deepest, darkest things come out, right?
No one does it.
Why the wrestling? I think it's because
God wanted a physical demonstration
of what Jacob had been doing his entire life.
Jacob, I'm going to wrestle you.
I'm going to confront you and do some things in your life,
do some deep things in your life.
I'm going to do that in the form of wrestling.
Not the wrestling I like, right?
I like the WWE, cheap, artificial, choreographed, like, it's fake.
I know it's fake.
Look at the person next to you and say wrestling is fake, right?
I know it's fake, right?
It's not that kind of wrestling.
It's the aggressive.
It's the brutal.
It's the tiring.
Has anyone actually wrestled here?
have you really no okay i mean you've wrestled like gym class or something like that like a gym
segment like semester thing no no one wrestling is really tiring like it's so exhausting like you're
trying to grapple with this guy or this girl and and you're like grappling and you're wrestling
and all this kind of stuff when you wrestle properly it's tiring it's exhausting it drains
you of everything that you have and i think god chose to wrestle jacob because this is what he had
been doing spiritually or emotionally or whatever in every area of his life up until now.
He had been wrestling to get this blessing. He had been wrestling to get these good things in
his life. He had been wrestling because no one would give it to him. So he had to take it by
force. And God is showing, hey, this is what you've been doing. You've been striving. You've been
striving. You've been striving. Aren't you tired of it yet? You're coming to the end of it. You
can't wrestle your way out of meeting your brother. And I think God wanted to show him
something in this as he's physically doing what he's been spiritually doing for all of his entire
life he's wrestling with him i do i do need to make this point god doesn't struggle because god
is weak look at the person next to him say god is not weak he doesn't struggle against jacob because
oh my gosh jacob is this really really profound good wrestler you know no it's because god wants
to do something god wants him to be drained god wants to make a point in jacob's life and that's
why he lets this go on as long as he does. Still in this moment, Jacob is wrestling, and Jacob
is wrestling for a blessing that he wanted, right? He's not sure who this is, and eventually, I mean,
he might get to that point, but he's wrestling for blessing. But ultimately, right, whether he knew
this to be God or not, he has this one specific thing in mind. God, I need you to bless me in this
way. He might not have understood that this was God, but he wanted this blessing right then and
there. In a few verses earlier, in verses 9 through 12, it says this, and Jacob said,
But O God of my father, Abraham and God of my father Isaac, O Lord who said to me,
we turn to your country and to your kindred, that I may do you good.
I am not worthy of the least of all the deeds of steadfast love and all the faithfulness you have shown to your servant.
For with only my staff I cross this Jordan, and now I have become two camps.
Verse 11, this is what he wants.
Please deliver me from the hand of my brother, from the hand of Esau,
for I fear him that he may come and attack me, the mothers with the children.
but he said i will surely do you good and make your offspring as the sand of the sea which cannot
be numbered for multitude okay i don't know it's night i think that's also why this happens at night
so that he doesn't fully understand that what he's wrestling with god at this point he finds out
later but he he's not sure yet but he wants this blessing and i don't know what kind of blessing
he was expecting from this man but from god this is the blessing that he wanted i just want to live
i don't want my brother to be angry with me or even if he's angry with me let him be not
angry enough to not kill me that's the blessing that jacob wanted but at the end of it what happens
god gives jacob a different more powerful more amazing blessing the blessing god gave is not
just security although later we discover esau doesn't kill him they hug they embrace they
seem to reconcile but the blessing god gave jacob your name shall no longer be called jacob
but Israel. This new name, especially as it's given to him, not by his parents, but by God
himself. I am changing your identity and I'm changing your destiny. In the past, you were
known as a cheat, as a deceiver, as someone who grabs the heel of his older brother. But here in
this moment, I'm going to tell you, and if you see the footnotes, you can see certain things like,
oh he strives with God or God strives like that's something that the word Israel can mean but God
describes it specifically here for you have striven with God and with men and have prevailed
the blessing that God gives Jacob slash Israel is this you're not you're no longer going to become
known for your deception and you're cheating and you're lying and you're scheming and you're
manipulating, you're going to be known as the guy who overcame. Israel has struggled and overcome.
You'll see that when he finishes up with Esau later, he's overcome. The relationship is
reconciled. He's overcome and he's become his own people. And I think this is also a promise in the
future. When Israel, when you strive, when your descendants strive, when the people of God
strive, they will struggle and overcome. This is a far better identity and destiny than the guy who
cheats and deceives and steals.
Can I draw your attention to this truth?
We are who we are
because God is who
he is. Why is
Jacob the receiver of these promises
and blessings? Because
God is a promise maker
and a promise keeper.
And for us, this is where I want to draw our attention out of the
Old Testament and into the New.
When we think about our identities,
when we think about who Christ has
called us, not to do, but to be,
we can think about God we can think about Jesus and we can think hey if he is this if they are this
then we can trust that our identity is this when Jesus was asked help us to pray teach us to pray
the first words out of his mouth when he's teaching them to pray are what our father
if god is a father who are we as children we are his sons we are his daughters if god is a father
and that's just his nature that's just his character that's just who he is then we are his
beloved children if jesus calls himself and john if he calls himself the good shepherd then who are
we? We're the sheep. We are the sheep who Jesus takes care of. He feeds us. He takes care of us.
He watches over us. And in that passage in John, he talks about the good shepherd lays down his life
for his sheep so his sheep can live. Jesus being the good shepherd means we are taken care of
even at the cost of Jesus's life. We are loved and we are cared for because we are his sheep.
When it says in 1 John that God is love, then we can trust.
We don't have to earn anything.
It's not that it's a conditional love.
God will love us if X, Y, and Z.
But if God in his nature, if God in his identity is love, then who are you and me?
We are his beloved.
When we talk about identity, yes, you can have all of these other markers.
Are you a millennial, Gen Z, Gen Alpha?
Are you some kind of ethnic group?
Are you some kind of major arts, major music, whatever, engineering?
Are you a Michigan Wolverine?
Yeah.
You guys care a lot about your team and football and Wolverines.
Yay, go blue.
Okay.
Sorry, someone called me out for having a profile picture about Western Michigan.
Anyway, sorry if that's hurting a wound.
Where am I going?
Identity.
I'm not trying to get rid of these other labels and markers.
That's great if you have some of these.
Are you a son or daughter to your parents?
Sure.
Are you a sibling, older brother, sister, younger brother, sister to the people?
Are you an only child?
Right?
That's all fine.
But at the core of it, at the core of who you are, if your core is not something like
I am God's beloved, I am God's loved son, God's loved daughter, I have done nothing
to earn his love, but I have been adopted and chosen by him.
If that's not your core, then I worry, I fear for you that your core identity is not good
enough, is not stable enough, is not
strong enough to endure everything that life
is going to throw at you.
But if we understand that
God gives us
this identity, and God is
unchanging,
then no matter what life gives,
what life throws at us, no matter what curses people
try to throw at us, no matter what difficulty
comes up in life, that our identity
is secure, that we rest,
that we have peace, saying, no matter
what happens, no matter what people think of me,
and I know that God loves me
and that's enough
I don't have a lot of time to talk about this point
how do we find this identity
but I think there's a quote from C.S. Lewis
that talks about it well enough for me
he writes this in mere Christianity
your real
new self
which is Christ's
and also yours
and yours just because it is his
will not come
as long as you are looking for it
it will come when you are looking for him.
Does that sound strange?
The same principle holds, you know, for more everyday matters.
Even in social life, you will never make a good impression on other people
until you stop thinking about what sort of impression you're making.
Even in literature and art,
no man who bothers about originality will ever be original,
whereas if you simply try to tell the truth
without caring two pence how often it has been told before,
you will, nine times out of ten, become original without ever having noticed it.
The principle runs through all life from top to bottom.
Give up yourself and you'll find your real self.
Lose your life and you will save it.
Submit to death, death of your ambitions and favorite wishes every day
and death of your whole body in the end.
Submit with every fiber of your being and you will find eternal life.
Keep back nothing.
nothing that you have not given away will really be yours
nothing in you that has not died will ever be raised from the dead
look for yourself and you'll find in the long run
only hatred, loneliness, despair, rage, ruin and decay
but look for Christ and you'll find him
and with him everything else thrown in
friends the paradoxical thing is this
We can't find our identity by finding it.
We can't search for identity by searching for it.
We can't discover our identity by discovering it.
We can't find our identity by building it ourselves.
At least the good, true, stable, whole, healed, complete identity,
core identity of who we are, we can't find that unless we go looking for him.
And again, the more we know God, the more we know things like he is a father, he is a good shepherd, he is love, he is the one who cares, he is the one who goes after the lost, he is the one who does this and this and that.
This is who he is.
The more we find God, the more that we can understand, oh, no, this is who I am because God is who he is.
So again, back to the one thing of God wants to bless you with a new identity in Christ.
Can I encourage you with two things?
One, behold, to reflect on God's identity and your identity regularly, and to believe.
To choose to believe who God says you are, not who others or even yourself, who you say you are.
If you were here this past Sunday, we continued on Ephesians and talked about the spiritual blessings that we have in Christ.
And the big one is really the idea of adoption, that we are chosen to be his beloved sons and daughters.
And Pastor Pete shared these two resources with us.
We'll just throw the links both on screen,
hmsezy.tech slash identity and birthright.
These are documents that compile from Scripture.
I don't know how well you feel like you know Scripture,
how well you feel like you know the Bible.
If I asked you to find in the Bible,
like, hey, well, who does the Bible tell you that you are?
I don't know if you have a good, strong list.
And so these are pulled from resources that we've had
and that we've used in the past, different things.
Like some of you know, a freedom class.
One of them is from there.
But I would encourage you, I revisit these, even for myself, every once in a while, to look at these, to slowly read through them, and to consider, God, who do you need to remind me of, that I am this because you are who you are.
I'm going to do things a little bit differently tonight to wrap up.
So, again, these spaces, these times are important in that we like having these Fridays to have a little bit more time embedded into them to reflect if God is speaking to us personally, to process.
I think the worst things that can happen in situations like these are for us to enter a room, to hear some things, and for it to go one ear out the other.
We leave the room and we don't really let the truths or maybe what God is speaking to us, we don't really let that change us.
So we want to do things a little bit differently tonight.
I'm going to ask us to take some time.
I'm going to ask the team,
can you just throw the list of questions pulled from the message?
We just have, you know, I share these questions throughout the message.
If these are helpful, reflect through them.
If not, just reflect for yourself.
Man, who am I? Who do I think that I am?
You know, go through some of the themes.
Other people said things.
Have you tried to do things?
Have you tried to perform or achieve things?
We want to give a good chunk of time just for us to reflect
because, again, God does that deep work when we're alone with him.
Now, I know that there's a number of us in this room.
I'm not saying physically alone tonight.
But for us even to have some time to be spiritually alone with him,
not talking, not singing, not praying.
I mean, sorry, pray, pray, pray.
but for us just to be alone with god even if it's physically with other people for us to be alone
with god and to deal with him we have some space in this room you can spread out you don't have to
feel like you're you know in a sardine can with the people next to you if you want to spread out
there's room in the back or whatever if some of you like sitting to reflect do that some of you
like walking around to reflect do that if some of you are reflected through journaling man do that
If you have journals with you, if you have something to write on, we'd encourage that.
If some of us just need time to be silent and alone with God for a while, we'd encourage that as well.
But what I want to ask us is this, is to take some time to have some time of reflection.
Not only to answer questions like this, but maybe even more importantly,
if you never get to answer any of these questions, but you hear God speak to you tonight,
saying, I want you to know how much I love you.
I want it so much
that it becomes your defining identity
when people ask you
who you are, you might tell them your name
hey, I'm Josh and I am beloved by God
that deep
core essential nature of who
I am is
loved by God
if you hear that from God, I hope that that happens
even if you reflect
through these questions, I hope that you still hear God's voice
more importantly than anything
but what we're going to do tonight, again, we'll have some time to reflect
For some of us, it's not that we don't mentally know,
oh, no, I know I'm loved by God up here,
but it's something blocking from up here to down here.
And so for us, maybe these questions can help get to the core of,
oh, these are the obstacles that refuse to take it from my brain to my heart.
I'm loved by God, but I don't feel loved by God.
I'm loved by God, but that's not my core identity.
Well, what's getting in the way?
And maybe this can shine a light.
Maybe there's other things that I didn't touch on today.
but maybe there's some things that are in the way
that are stopping you from saying,
no, I know in my core identity I am beloved by God.
So we want to have a good chunk of time to reflect,
to have this time to journal, to process, to whatever else.
We'll have this.
There'll just be some music kind of playing in the background.
We just like to do this to kind of cover up the random sirens
that come across Huron and who knows what the fire
or the ambulances are going after.
or even to, you know, just cover up coughing or whatever else.
And we'd just like to, just also to set the mood to be like,
hey, this is a worshipful environment.
This is a prayerful environment.
So we'll have some music playing in the background for that.
We'll have a chunk of time for us to reflect,
to be with God, to wrestle with him even.
After some time, it gathers us back together.
We'll just sing maybe one or two songs
just to declare some truths about, man, this is who we are.
for me worship through song is one way where i can fight to remember fight to behold these truths
about who i am and who god is so we'll do just a just a brief time just to speak and sing those
truths and then afterwards we're going to end in our life groups again if you're not part of a life
group just join one if you know someone join them if not just join any and for us to in our life
groups have some time to share with one another and more importantly if i can make sure leaders
is if we can just make sure to have time
to pray for one another,
to pray these identity markers over one another,
to say no matter what you've understood about yourself,
I want to pray for you
that more than anything you would understand,
no, your core identity is you belong to God.
And we want to pray for that for each other.
So we'll leave some space over for that.
Can I pray?
And then we'll go into some time of reflection tonight
just to wrestle with God here.
God, I confess even for myself,
this is something I'm still struggling with.
It's hard to, on a day-to-day, on Monday afternoon,
it's hard to remember, wait, no, I really am beloved by God,
when there's so many other things to think about.
God, even now, I still get crushed at times
when I don't feel like I'm living up to my other identities.
As a husband, as a father, as a pastor, as a person,
am I good enough, am I doing enough?
God, for all of us,
whether we're actively feeling the struggle tonight or not,
I know that our identity has to come from you.
If it comes from any other source,
it can be crushing,
it can be even disappointing
if we achieve those identities
and we find, oh, there's nothing at the end of it afterwards.
But God, if it comes from you,
because you're good, because you're loving,
because you are unchanging,
then I know, yes, life still might get,
might be difficult, there still might be grieving
or processing of other things to do,
sure. I'm not saying everything
is going to be beautiful and perfect in every way.
But God, I know
at least if our core identity is wrapped up in
you, in who you are and who we
are because of you,
I know that goes a long way to
say, I can rest,
I can have peace,
because my identity
is that I belong to God.
And so God, if there are difficulties,
if there are obstacles, I pray that you
use this time to bring them
to the surface, not just so that we can
be aware of them, but as we pray
through them and as we bring them to you, you could break
some of those.
Break through
so that our identity, our core identity,
our main identity, is I am
loved by God. Help us
tonight. In Jesus' name.
Amen.